<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true report of all the successe of Famagosta, of the antique writers called Tamassus, a citie in Cyprus In the which the whole order of all the skirmishes, batteries, mines, and assaultes geuen to the sayd fortresse, may plainly appeare. Moreouer the names of the captaines, and number of the people slaine, as well of the Christians as of the Turkes: likewise of them who were taken prisoners: from the beginning of the sayd seege vntill the end of the same. Englished out of Italian by William Malim. With certaine notes of his and expositions of all the Turkishe wordes herein necessary to be knowen, placed in the margent, with a short description also of his of the same iland.</title>
            <title>Assedio, et presa di Famagosta. English</title>
            <author>Martinengo, Nestore, Conte.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 434:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true report of all the successe of Famagosta, of the antique writers called Tamassus, a citie in Cyprus In the which the whole order of all the skirmishes, batteries, mines, and assaultes geuen to the sayd fortresse, may plainly appeare. Moreouer the names of the captaines, and number of the people slaine, as well of the Christians as of the Turkes: likewise of them who were taken prisoners: from the beginning of the sayd seege vntill the end of the same. Englished out of Italian by William Malim. With certaine notes of his and expositions of all the Turkishe wordes herein necessary to be knowen, placed in the margent, with a short description also of his of the same iland.</title>
                  <title>Assedio, et presa di Famagosta. English</title>
                  <author>Martinengo, Nestore, Conte.</author>
                  <author>Malim, William, 1533-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Daye,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1572.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Martinengo, Nestore, conte. L'assedio, et presa di Famagosta.</note>
                  <note>This edition has signatures: A-F⁴ G²  (-G2).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The seege of Famagosta.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Famagusta (Cyprus) --  History --  Siege, 1571 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The true Report of all the ſucceſſe of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> of the antique writers called <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſus,</hi> a Citie in <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the which the whole or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all the ſkirmiſhes, batteries, mines, and aſſaultes geuen to the ſayd Fortreſſe, may plainly appeare.</p>
            <p>Moreouer the names of the Captaines, and number of the people ſlaine, as well of the Chriſtians as of the Turkes: likewiſe of them who were taken priſoners: from the beginning of the ſayd ſeege vntill the end of the fame.</p>
            <p>¶ Engliſhed out of Italian by <hi>William Malim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ With certaine notes of his and expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all the Turkiſhe wordes herein neceſſary to be knowen, placed in the margent, with a ſhort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription alſo of his of the ſame Iland.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>Iohn Daye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AN. 1572.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the right honourable and his ſingular good Lorde, and onely Patrone the Earle of Leiceſter, Baron of Denbigh, Knight of the honourable order of the Garter, one of the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt honourable priuie Counſell. &amp;c. <hi>William Malim</hi> wiſheth long health with encreaſe of honour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bene a naturall inſtinct (right honourable and mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall good Lorde) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed in noble perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages hartes, much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and confirmed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by cuſtome, for them to ſéeke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, by ſome meanes in their life, by the which, they after their death, might deliuer ouer their name to their poſteritie: leaſt otherwiſe with their body, their fame alſo altogether might perchaunce be buried. Vpon the which conſideration we read many notable, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thinges to haue bene erected in time paſt of noble perſonages (hauing had wealth at will) in ſuch ſort, that not onely certain ruines of the ſame ſumptuous workes builded ſo many hundred yeares paſt, doe ſtill remaine, but alſo the moſt part of thoſe princes the authors of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do continually by them dwell in our memoryes. As the <hi>Pyramides</hi> made at <hi>Memphis,</hi> or neare the famous Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Nilus,</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great expences of the Kings of Egypt: the Tower called <hi>Pharia,</hi> made in the Iland of <hi>Pharos</hi> by King <hi>Ptolomee:</hi> the walles of <hi>Babylon,</hi> made or at the leaſt réedified by Quéene <hi>Semiramis: Dianas</hi> Church
<pb facs="tcp:12662:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
at <hi>Epheſus</hi> builded by all the noble perſons of <hi>Aſia: Mauſolus</hi> Toome or Sepulcher, made by his wife Quéen of <hi>Caria: Coloſſus Solis</hi> placed at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not by what Princes charge, but made by the handes of <hi>Cares Lindius</hi> ſcholler to <hi>Lyſippus:</hi> and the Image of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> made of Yuerye by the handes of the ſkilfull workeman <hi>Phydias.</hi> The which monumentes made of barbarous and heathen Princes to redéeme them ſelues from obliuion, deſerued both for the magnificence, and perfecte workmanſhip of the ſame, to be accompled in thoſe dayes as the <hi>7.</hi> wonders of the world. Since the which time, an eaſier, readier, and lighter way, being alſo of more continuance then the former, hath ben found out, namely, Letters, which were firſt inuented by the Caldies and Egyptians, as we read, and augmented ſince by others, to our great benefite, and now laſt of all (no long time paſt) the ſame to haue bene committed to Printers Preſſes, to the greateſt perfection of the ſame: men being firſt enforced to write their actes and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in beaſtes ſkinnes dryed, in barkes of trées, or otherwiſe perchaunce as vnreadily. By the which bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of Letters (now reduced into Print) we ſée how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie a thing it is, and hath bene for noble perſons, to liue for euer by the helpe of learned men. For the memorye of thoſe two worthy and valiaunt Captaines <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Hannibal</hi> had bene long before this preſent quite forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, except <hi>Titus Liuius,</hi> or ſome ſuch learned Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher had written of them in time. And <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> him ſelfe that great conquerour had nothing bene ſpoken of, had not <hi>Q. Curtius,</hi> or ſome other like by his learned ſtile reuiued the remembraunce of him, and called backe againe his doinges to his poſteritie. For the which cauſe we ſée commonly in all ages learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be much made of by noble perſonages, as that rare paterne of learning <hi>Aristotle,</hi> to haue bene greatly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of that former renowmed Monarche <hi>Alexander:</hi> who affirmed openly, that he was more bound to his
<pb facs="tcp:12662:3"/>
Maiſter <hi>Aristotle,</hi> then to King <hi>Philip</hi> his father, becauſe the one had well framed his minde, the other onely his body. Many other like examples I could alledge at this preſent, if I knew not vnto whom I now wrote, or in what. For your honour being ſkilfull in hiſtories, and ſo familiarly acquainted with the matter it ſelfe, that is in ſtill intertaining learned men with all courteſie, I ſhould ſeeme to light a candle at noone tyde, to put you in remembrance of the one, or to exhort you to do the other, dayly being accuſtomed to performe the ſame. <hi>Craſſus</hi> ſayth in <hi>Tullies</hi> firſt booke, <hi>De Oratore:</hi> that a Lawyers houſe is the Oracle of the whole Citie. But I can iuſtly witneſſe, that for theſe <hi>5.</hi> yeares laſt paſt, ſince my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from my trauell beyond the ſeas, that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips lodging in the Court (where I through your vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued goodneſſe to my great comfort do dayly frequent) hath bene a continuall receptacle or harbour for all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men comming from both the eyes of this Realme, Cambridge, and Oxforde (of the which Vniuerſitie your Lordſhip is Chauncellor) to their great ſatiſfaction of minde, and ready diſpatch of their ſutes. Eſpecially for Preachers and Miniſters of true Religion: of the which you haue bene from time to time not onely a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer, but an earneſt furtherer, and protector: ſo that theſe two nurſeries of learning (in one of the which I haue before this ſpent part of my time, that I may ſpeake boldly what I thinke) ſhould wrong your honour great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and much forget them ſelues, if by all meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they ſhould not héerafter (as at this preſent to their ſmall powers many well learned gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them do) labour and trauell in ſhewing of them ſelues thankfull, to reuerence and honour your Lordſhip, and honeſt their owne names: whoſe ſtudies certainly would ſodainly decay and fall flat, if they were not helde vp by ſuch noble proppes, and had not ſome ſure anckerholdes in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe to leane vnto. How ready dayly your trauell is, and hath long bene beſides to benefite all other perſons,
<pb facs="tcp:12662:4"/>
in whom any ſparke of vertue or honeſtie remaineth, I néede not labour to expreſſe, the world knowing already the ſame. But whoſoeuer they be, that in all their life time haue an eſpeciall care by all meanes to profite as many as they be able and hurt none, do not onely a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable acte, but lead a perfecte and very godly life. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Strabo</hi> affirmeth this moſt truely to be ſpoken of them: <hi>Mortales tum demum Deos imitari, cum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifici fuerint.</hi> Great commendation vndoubtedly it bringeth to any noble perſonage, that as the Moone, that light and brightnes which ſhe receaueth of the Sunne, is wont preſently to ſpread abroad vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the earth, to the refreſhing and comforting of all inferiour and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall thinges bearing life: ſo for him, to beſtow all that fauour and credite, which he hath gotten at the Princes handes, to the helpe and reliefe of the worthy and néedy. Great is the force (my right honourable Lorde) of true Vertue, which cauſeth them as <hi>Tully</hi> writeth in his booke <hi>De Amicitia,</hi> to be loued and honoured oft of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which neuer ſawe them. Whereof I neuer had better proofe (I take God and mine owne conſcience to witneſſe, the which I declared alſo to certaine of my frendes as ſoone as I returned) then at my laſt being at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord. <hi>1564.</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I ofte reſorting (as occaſion ſerued) to the right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Chriſtian Ambaſſadors, whileſt I made my abode there (namely vnto <hi>Monſeur Antonio Petrimol,</hi> léegger there for the King of <hi>Fraunce, <hi>Sig. M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor Bragadino,</hi>
               </hi> for the Segniorye of <hi>Venice, <hi>Sig. Lorenzo Giustiniano,</hi>
               </hi> for the ſtate of <hi>Scio,</hi> or <hi>Chios,</hi> and <hi>Sig. Albertacio delli Alberti,</hi> for the Duke of <hi>Florence</hi>) heard them often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ſpeake very honourably of your Lordſhip, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your other good inclinations of nature, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your liberalitie, and courteous intreating of diuers of their frendes and countreymen, which vpon ſundry oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions had bene here in this our Realme. So that to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, all men iuſtly fauour your honourable dealinges
<pb facs="tcp:12662:4"/>
and deſertes: and I for my part haue reuerenced and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured the ſame euermore both here at home, &amp; elſwhere abroad, wiſhing often to haue had ſome iuſt occaſion to pay part of that in good will, which my ſlender abilitie wil neuer ſuffer me fully to diſcharge. For vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould I ſooner preſent any thing any way, eſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning matters done abroad, then vnto your Lordſhip, by whom I was much cheriſhed abroad in my trauell, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſince my returne here at home? For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which cauſe I haue enterpriſed (hoping greatly of your Lordſhips fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour herein) to clothe and ſet forth a few Italian Newes in our Engliſhe attyre, being firſt moued therunto by the right worſhipfull Maiſter <hi>D. Wilſon</hi> Maiſter of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Requeſts, your honors aſſured truſty frend, a great and painfull furtherer of learning, whom I, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for diuers reſpectes ought to reuerence: who remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that I had bene at <hi>Cyprus,</hi> was willing that my penne ſhould trauell about the Chriſtian &amp; Turkiſhe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, which there lately haue happened: perſwading him ſelfe, that ſomewhat therby I might benefite this our natiue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. Againſt whoſe reaſonable motion I could not greatly wraſtle, hazarding rather my ſlender ſkill in attempting &amp; perfourming this his requeſted taſke, then he through my refuſall thereof ſhould ſéeme to want any iotte of my good will. In offering vp the which newes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I ſhall preſent no new thing to your honour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are ſo well acquainted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Italian copy, as I know: yet I truſt your Lordſhip will not miſlike, that the ſame which is both pleaſant to read, and ſo neceſſary to be knowen for diuers of our Captaines and other our countreymen, which are ignoraunt in the Italian toung, may thus now ſhewe it ſelfe abroad, couered vnder the wing of your Lordſhips protection. Certainly it moueth me much to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of thoſe <hi>3.</hi> notable Ilands, to the great diſcomfort of all Chriſtendome, to thoſe Helliſh Turkes, Horſeleches of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloud: namely <hi>Rhodes</hi> beſéeged on S. Iohn Baptiſt day, and taken on S. Iohns
<pb facs="tcp:12662:5"/>
day the Euangeliſt, being the <hi>27.</hi> of December. <hi>1522. Scio</hi> or <hi>Chios</hi> being loſt ſince my being there, taken of <hi>Piali Baſsà</hi> with <hi>80.</hi> Gallies, the <hi>17.</hi> of Aprill. <hi>1566.</hi> And now laſt of all not onely <hi>Famagoſta</hi> the chéefe holde and fortreſſe in <hi>Cyprus</hi> to haue bene loſt of the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the <hi>15.</hi> of Auguſt laſt paſt. <hi>1571.</hi> (the chéefe Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Captaines of them being hewen in ſunder by the commaundement of that tyraunt <hi>Mustafà Baſsà</hi>) but all the whole Iland alſo to be conquered by thoſe cruell Turkes, auncient profeſſed enemies to all Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. In the which euill ſucceſſe (comming to vs as I take it for our offences) as I lament the generall loſſe: ſo I am ſurely penſiue to vnderſtand by this too true a report of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vile death of <hi>2.</hi> particular noble gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Venice, <hi>Sig. M. Lorenzo Tiepolo,</hi>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Sig. M. Giouanni Antonio Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini:</hi> of both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which I in my trauel was very courteouſly vſed, the former of them being then (as now alſo he was in this ouerthrow) Gouernour of <hi>Baffo</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> the other Captaine of one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Caſtels at <hi>Corſyra</hi> in Grece, now called <hi>Corfu.</hi> But thinges paſt, are paſt amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they could neuer die more honourably, then in the defence of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. Beſides that the late blowes, which the Turkes haue receaued ſince this their fury, in token of Gods wrath againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, much comforteth euery Chriſtian hart. Moreouer this vniforme preparation which is certainly concluded, and forthwith looked for, by very many Chriſtian Princes (would God by all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally) againſt theſe barborous Mahometiſtes: whoſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie and beaſtly behauour I partly know, and am able to iudge of, hauing bene in Turkye amongeſt them more then <hi>8.</hi> monethes together. Whoſe vnfaythfulnes alſo and breach of promiſſe, as the Venetians manly courage in defence of them ſelues, and their fortreſſe, your honour may eaſily read in this ſhort treatiſe and ſmall handfull of leaues, I hauing ſet downe alſo a ſhort deſcription of the Iland of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> for the better vnderſtanding of the whole matter. The which I not onely moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeche
<pb facs="tcp:12662:5"/>
your honour now fauourably to accept as an earneſt penny of more to come, and of my preſent good will: but with your accuſtomed goodneſſe towardes me, to defend the ſame againſt ſuch perſons, whoſe tounges too readily role ſometime againſt other mens painfull trauells, perſwading them ſelues to purchaſe the ſooner ſome credite of learning with the ruder ſort, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troling and ouerdaintie ſifting of other mens laboured taſkes. For I know in all ages to be found as well Baſiliſkes, as Elephantes. Thus nothing doubting of your readye ayde herein, as I aſſuredly truſt of your honours fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptation of this my poore preſent, wiſhing long life with the encreaſe of Gods holy ſpirite to your Lordſhip and to all your moſt honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie (vnto whom I haue wholy dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe by mine owne choiſe and election for euer) I, crauing pardon for my former bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, moſt humbly thus take my leaue.</p>
            <p>From Lambheth the <hi>23.</hi> of March. An. <hi>1572.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶ Your honours moſt humble and faithfull ſeruaunt for euer, <hi>William Malim.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="description_of_Cyprus">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:6"/>
            <head>¶ A breefe deſcription of the Iland of Cyprus: by the which not onely the Venetians title why they haue ſo long enioyed it, but alſo the Turkes, whereby now he claimeth it, may plainly appeare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Iland of Cyprus is inuironed with diuers ſeas. For Westward it is waſhed with the ſea called Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philium: Southward, with the Sea Ægyptium: on the Eaſt part, with the Sea Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium: and Northward, with the Sea called Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licium. The which Iland in time paſt had diuers names: called once Acamantis, as Sabellicus witneſſeth: Philonides maketh mention, that it was called ſometime Ceraſis, Xenagoras wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that it was named Aspelia, Amathuſa, and Macaria. There were in time paſte 15. Cities or famous Townes in it, but now very fewe, amongſt the which Famagoſta is the chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and ſtrongeſt, ſituated by the Sea ſide. There is alſo Nicoſia, which was wont, by the trafficke of Marchauntes, to be very wealthy: beſides the Citie of Baffo, Arnica, Saline, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſo, Milopotomo, and Epiſcopia. Timoſthenes affirmeth, that this Iland in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe is 400. and 29. miles, and Arthemidorus writeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be 162. miles, meaſuring of it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:12662:6"/>
Eaſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt betwixt two promontories named Dimareta &amp; Acamanta. This Iland is thought to be very riche, abundant of Wine, Oyle, Grain, Pitch, Roſin, Allum, Salt, &amp; of diuers precious ſtones pleaſant, profitable, &amp; neceſſary for mans vſe, &amp; much freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of Marchantes of Syria, vnto the which it lieth very neare. It hath bene as Plinie writeth, ioyned ſometime with Syria, as Sicilia hath bene alſo with Italy. It was a long time ſubiecte vnto the Romaines, after, to the Perſians, and to the Souldan of Ægypt. And laſt of all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians haue enioyed it of late a long time, in this order following. In the yeare of our Lord. 1470. Iohn King of the ſayd Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſonne to Ianus of Luſignian had by Hellen his wife, which was of the Emperiall houſe of Paleologus one daughter onely called Charlotta, &amp; a baſtard called Iames: the which Iames was afterward conſecrated Biſhop of Nicoſia. This Charlotta was maried firſt to the King of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall, of whom he had no iſſue, ſo that he being dead, Lewes Duke of Sauoy (to whom ſhe was the ſecond time maried) ſonne to Lewes the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of that name (vnto whom the ſayd Iland by the right of this his wife Charlotta did apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) had the poſſeſsion of the ſame. Iames the baſtard as ſoone as his father was dead, of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb facs="tcp:12662:7"/>
became a Soldier, and with an army wanne the Jland, making it his owne by force. This Duke of Sauoy hearing theſe newes, with a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of well appointed ſoldiers, arriued ſhortly after in Cyprus, &amp; recouering againe the Iland, compelled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baſtard to flye forthwith ouer to the Souldan of Ægypt. Who making him ſelfe his ſubiecte, in time ſo wrought and tempered the matter, that the Souldan in perſon at his requeſt paſſed ouer into Cyprus, beſeeged Duke Lewes in the Caſtell of Nicoſia, &amp; at length compelled him to depart, leauing his kingdome. So that this Biſhop became againe King of this Iland: who ſhortly after cleauing to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made a league of frendſhip with them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by their conſent one Catherina the daughter of Marco Cornaro, which Catherine the Senate of Venice adopted vnto them ſoone after as their daughter. This Biſhop not long after ſickned, &amp; died, leauing this his wife with child, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not long after his fathers death. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which meanes the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians making them ſelues the next heires to Catherina by the lawe of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tooke vnto them the poſſeſsion of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and haue kept, and enioyed the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt this 100. yeares. Now this great Turke called Sultan Selim in the right of the Souldan
<pb facs="tcp:12662:7"/>
of Ægypt, whom his grandfather (called alſo Sultan Selim) conquered, pretendeth a right ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vnto it, and now as you may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by reading of this ſhort treatiſe hath by conquest obtained the ſame. Whom, I pray the euerliuing God, if it be his holy will, ſhortly to roote out from thence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignoraunt (gentle Reader) how hard a matter it is for any one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to write that, which ſhould pleaſe and ſatiſfie all perſons, we being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly of ſo diuers opinions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary iudgementes: againe Tully affirming, to bee a very difficult thing, to finde out any matter which in his owne kinde may be in all reſpectes perfecte. Wherefore I truſt by your own iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I ought of reaſon to be the ſooner pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (my tranſlation being preciſely tyed to mine authors meaning) if any thieg herein beſides be thought to be wanting: I hauing learned by the way, how comberous a thing it is, to turne the ſelfe ſame matter out of the Italian language into our countrey ſpeech. But who doth what he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly can, is bound to no more. And I now at the requeſt of others (who put me in minde, that I was not onely borne vnto my ſelf) haue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that in the end, which I promiſed &amp; was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. With what paine &amp; diligence, I refer me to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are ſkilfull in the Italian toung, or may the better iudge, if it pleaſe them to trye the ſame, caſting a ſide this exampler. I ſpeake not arrogantly, I take God to witnes: but mens pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trauels ought not lightly to be condemned: nor ſurely at any time are wont to be of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or diſcrete. By whoſe gentle acceptation, if theſe my preſent doinges be now ſupported, I will perſwade my ſelfe that I haue reaped ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fruite of my trauell. Vnto whom with all my hart I wiſh proſperous ſucceſſe in all their affaires.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>AN. 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Jn Turchas precatio.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vmme Deus ſuccurre tuis, miſereſce tuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
            <l>Et ſubeat gentis te noua cura tuae.</l>
            <l>Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> das tantoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Rex magne, laboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</l>
            <l>In nos vibrabit tela quoſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Sathan?</l>
            <l>Ante Rhodum, mox inde Chium, nunc deni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Cyprum</l>
            <l>Turcharum cepit ſanguinolenta manus.</l>
            <l>Muſtafa foedifragus partes graſſatur in omnes,</l>
            <l>Et Veneta Cypriam ſtrage cruentat humum.</l>
            <l>Nec finem imponit ſceleri, mollitué furorem,</l>
            <l>Nec niſi potato ſanguine pactus, abit.</l>
            <l>Qualis, quae nunquàm niſi plena tumenſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> cruore</l>
            <l>Sanguiſuga obſeſſam mittit hirudo cutem.</l>
            <l>Torturam ſequitur tortura, cruor<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> cruorem,</l>
            <l>Et caedem admiſſam caedis alîus amor.</l>
            <l>Saeuit inops animi, nec vel ſe temperat ipſe,</l>
            <l>Vel manus indomitum noſtra domare poteſt.</l>
            <l>At tu, magne Pater, tumidum diſperde Tyrannum,</l>
            <l>Nec ſine mactari ſemper ouile tuum.</l>
            <l>Exulet hoc monſtrum, ne ſanguine terra redundet,</l>
            <l>Excutiant<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nouum Cypria regna iugum.</l>
            <l>Et quod Chriſticolae foedus pepigere Monarchae,</l>
            <l>Id fauſtum nobis omnibus eſſe velis.</l>
            <l>Tu pugna illorum pugnas, &amp; bella ſecundes,</l>
            <l>Captiuoſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tibi ſubde per arma Scythas.</l>
            <l>Sic tuo per totum fundetur gloria mundum,</l>
            <l>Vnus ſic Chriſtus fiet, &amp; vna fides.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gulielmus Malim.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12662:9"/>
            <head>¶The true report of all the ſucceſſe of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> made by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earle <hi>Nestor Martinengo,</hi> vnto the renowmed Prince the Duke of <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>16.</hi> day of Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>1571.</hi> the Fleete which had brought the ayde vnto <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> departed from thence, wheras were found in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armie, but <hi>4000.</hi> footeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>800.</hi> of them choſen ſoldiers, &amp; <hi>3000.</hi> (accompting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citizens &amp; other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> villages) the reſt <hi>200.</hi> in number, were ſoldiers of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania.</hi> After the arriuall of the which ſuccour, the fortification of the Citie went more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently forward of all handes, then it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the whole garriſon, the Grecian Citizens inhabiting the towne, the gouerners and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines not withdrawing them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any kinde of labour, for the better incouragement and good example of others, both night and day ſearching the watch, to the intent with moſt carefull heedetaking they might beware of their enemies, againſt whom they made no ſallye out of the Citie to ſkirmiſh but very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, eſpecially to vnderſtand, when they might learne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent of the enemies. Whileſt we made this diligent prouiſion within the Citie, the Turkes without made no leſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb facs="tcp:12662:10"/>
of all thinges neceſſary fit to batter the fortreſſe with all, as in bringing out of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramania</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> with all ſpeede by the ſea, many Wollpackes, a great quantitie of wood and timber, diuers peeces of artilarye, ingens, and other thinges expedient for their purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">This word <hi>Baſsà,</hi> is a moſt honourable title amongeſt the Turkes, and ſignifieth as much with vs as a priuie cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller.</note>At the beginning of Aprill <hi>Halli Baſsà</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there with <hi>80.</hi> Gallies or thereabout in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, who brought thether that, which of our enemies was deſired, who ſoone after departing from thence, and leauing behinde hym <hi>30.</hi> Gallies, which continually tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported ſoldiers, munition, freſhe victuals, and other neceſſaries, beſides à great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caramuſalini</hi> be veſſels like vnto the French Gabards, which ſaile daily vpon the riuer of Bordeaux, which ſaile with a miſen or triangle ſaile.</note> 
               <hi>Caramuſalins,</hi> or Brigandins, great Hulkes called<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Maone</hi> be veſſels like vnto the great Hulkes, which come hether from Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, ſome of the which cary <hi>7.</hi> or <hi>8.</hi> hundreth tunnes a peece, flat, and broad, which ſaile ſome of them with <hi>7.</hi> miſens a peece.</note> 
               <hi>Maones,</hi> and large broad veſſels termed of them<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Palandrie</hi> be great flatte veſſels made like Feribotes to tranſporte horſe.</note> 
               <hi>Palandrie,</hi> which continually paſſed to and fro betwixt <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> &amp; other places there about, which they did with great ſpeed, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in feare of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian armie. And about the midſt of the ſame moneth, the Turkes cauſed to be brought out of the Citie of <hi>Nicoſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called <hi>Licoſia.</hi>
               </note> which they had wonne a little before, <hi>15.</hi> peeces of artilarye, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their army fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they were before, making ditches &amp; trenches neceſſary, incampt them ſelues in gardens, and toward the Weſt part of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> neare a place called <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pola.</hi> The <hi>25.</hi> of the ſame moneth they raiſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12662:10"/>
vp mountes to plant their artilary vpon, and cauſed trenches to be made for harquebuſers one very nigh an other, approching ſtill very neare the Citie, in ſuch order, as was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to ſtay the ſame, <hi>40.</hi> thouſand of their Pioners continually labouring there the moſt part of all the night. The intent of the enemie being then knowen, and in what part of the Citie he minded moſt to plant his batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we tooke diligent heede on the other part, to repaire &amp; fortifie all places neceſſary with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which cauſe we placed à great watch in that way, which was couered with à coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcharfe, and in the ſallies of their priuie Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns, for the defence of the ſaid cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terſcharfe there were new fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckers made, alſo Trauerſes called Butteriſſes, made vpon the Cortaine with one trench of Turues <hi>2.</hi> foote high and broad, the which was made on that ſide of the wall of the Citie, which was already battered with the ſhotte of the Turkes, with certaine loope holes for our Harquebuſers, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they defended the counterſcharfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sig. Bragadino</hi> was <hi>Proueditore,</hi> that is, Gouernour, and <hi>Sig. Baglione</hi> Generall of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> armie: both of them were noble men of Venice.</note> Two noble perſonages <hi>Bragadino</hi> and <hi>Baglione,</hi> perſonally tooke this charge on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the which meanes the Chriſtian affaires paſſed in very good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. All the bread for our ſoldiers was made in one ſtorehouſe, of the which the noble gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>Lorenzo Tiepolo</hi> Captaine of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baffo,</hi> of the auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, named <hi>Paphos,</hi> in the which Citie there was a ſumptuous Church dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Venus.</note> 
               <hi>Baffo</hi> had charge, who refuſed no paine, where he thought his trauaile might preuaile. In the Caſtell was placed that famous gentleman
<pb facs="tcp:12662:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Andrea Bragadino,</hi> who with à diligent garde had charge on that part of the Caſtell princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, next vnto the ſea ſide, trimming and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out new flanckers for the better defence of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Arſenall</hi> in Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; Venice, is the place for munition &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilary to lye in.</note> 
               <hi>Arſenall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A valiant Knight named <hi>Foito,</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed maſter of the Ordinance, who was ſlaine in à fewe dayes after in à ſkirmiſhe, whoſe gariſon the noble <hi>Bragadino <hi>Proueditore</hi>
               </hi> before named, preſently deliuered ouer to me. Three other Captaines were appointed ouer the wildefire with <hi>20.</hi> footemen for euery one of them, choſen out of the armie to vſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame as occaſion ſhould ſerue. The beſt peeces of Ordinance were brought forth vnto that ſide of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battery was lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for to be made: &amp; they made priuie fences to couer the better their Cannon ſhot withall. There was no want in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians to annoy their enemies in iſſuing often out of euery ſide againſt them, as well to hinder their determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, as to hurt them otherwiſe at diuers times. They alſo rendered to vs the like. For <hi>300.</hi> of the inhabitance of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> one time iſſuing out of the Citie, armed onely with their Swordes and Targets, with ſo many Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Harquebuſers alſo in their company, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued great dammage, becauſe the trenches of the enemies were made about ſo thicke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at the ſame preſent we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled them to flye, and ſlewe alſo many of them: yet they encreaſed to ſuch number, that they killed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12662:11"/>
               <hi>30.</hi> and hurt there <hi>60.</hi> of our company. For the which cauſe order was taken, that our men ſhould no more come forth of their holde, committing them ſelues to manifeſt perill to bid their enemies the baſe.</p>
            <p>The Turkes in proceſſe of time by litle and litle with their trenches, came at length to the toppe of the counterſcharfe, and hauing finiſhed their fortes the <hi>19.</hi> of May, began their batterye with <hi>10.</hi> fortes, hauing 74. peeces of great artilary within their cuſtodie, amongeſt the which there were <hi>4.</hi> Baſiliſkes (for ſo they terme them) of an immeaſurable greatnes, and began to batter from the gate <hi>Limiſſo</hi> vnto the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> and layde <hi>5.</hi> batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries againſt the towne, the one againſt the great high Turret of the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> which was battered with <hi>5.</hi> peeces of Ordinance moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon that forte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rocke, the other againſt the Cortaine it ſelfe of the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> battered by one forte with <hi>11.</hi> peeces: an other againſt the Keepe of <hi>Andruzzi</hi> with <hi>2.</hi> commaunders, which were aboue with one forte of <hi>11.</hi> other peeces: an other battery againſt the Turret of <hi>S. Nappa,</hi> the which was battered with <hi>4.</hi> Baſiliſkes. The gate of <hi>Limiſſo,</hi> which had one high commaunder alone, and à Brey and Cortaine without was battered by the fortes with <hi>33.</hi> peeces of artilary, whereas <hi>Mustafà</hi> him ſelfe generall of the Turkes armie tooke the charge in perſon. At the firſt they ſeemed not to care much to ſpoyle the walles, but ſhot
<pb facs="tcp:12662:12"/>
ſtill into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie, and againſt our Ordinance, which greatly galled them. Whereupon they, who were within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie, as well our ſoldiers, as the Grecians, as ſoone as the battery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, withdrawing them ſelues, came &amp; dwelt by the walles of the Citie, whereas they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from that time to the end of the ſiege. The noble <hi>Bragadino</hi> lodged in the Keepe of <hi>Andruzzi, <hi>Baglione</hi>
               </hi> in that warde of <hi>S. Nappa.</hi> The honorable <hi>Tiepolo</hi> in that which was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Campo Santo.</hi> Wherefore they being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to all that was done, both encouraged, and puniſhed the ſoldiers according to their deſertes. The right worſhipfull <hi>Luigi Martinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> was appointed cheefe ouer the Ordinance, who anſwering all mens expectation of him, with great courage deuided the charge therof vnto <hi>6.</hi> other inferiour Captaines, who tooke order and care for that company, and for the prouiſion of things neceſſary for the gunners: one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grecians being appointed to euery gate of the Citie for to attend vpon the ſeruice of the artilary. The valiant Captaine <hi>Franceſco Bagone</hi> warded at the Keepe, and at the great commaunder of the Arſenall. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Pietro Conte</hi> attended vpon the Cortaine, at the Commaunder of the <hi>Volti,</hi> and at the Keepe of <hi>Campo Santo.</hi> I for my part atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Commaunder of <hi>Campo Santo,</hi> and vpon the Commaunder of <hi>Andruzzi,</hi> and of the Cortaine, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turret of <hi>Santa Nappa.</hi> The Earle <hi>Hercole Martinengo</hi> attended vpon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12662:12"/>
the Commaunder of <hi>Santa Nappa,</hi> and to the whole Cortaine, vnto the gate of <hi>Limiſſo. <hi>Horatio</hi>
               </hi> Captaine of <hi>Veletri</hi> attended vpon the Brey and Cortaine, towardes the Bulwarke. Vpon the high Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunder of <hi>Limiſſo,</hi> which was more troubled then all the reſt, attended the Captain <hi>Roberto Maluezzi.</hi> At the ſame time, when the battery began (by the commiſſion of the honourable <hi>Bragadino</hi>) victuals were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and geuen to all the ſoldiers, as well Grecians, as Italians, &amp; Gunners: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wine, Pottage, Cheeſe, and Bakon: all the which thinges were brought to the walles as neede did require in very good order, ſo that no ſoldier there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Venetian Souſes or <hi>Soldi</hi> amount but to one pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Engliſhe.</note> ſpent any more in bread then <hi>2.</hi> ſouſes a day. They were payde at the end of euery <hi>30.</hi> dayes, with the great trauell of that right worſhipfull Venetian gentleman <hi>M. Giouanni Antonio Querini,</hi> who beſides this his ordinary charge was found preſent in all waightie and daungerous affaires to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great incouragement of our ſoldiers. And we made à counterbattery againſt our enemies for <hi>10.</hi> dayes ſpace, with ſo great rage, that we cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and deſtroyed <hi>15.</hi> of their beſt peeces, alſo we killed &amp; diſpatched of them about <hi>30.</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand at that ſeaſon, ſo that they were diſapoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at that time of their battery in that place, and were greatly diſmayed. But we foreſeing that we had no great ſtore of pouder left, there was made à reſtraint, and ſuch order taken, that <hi>30.</hi> peeces ſhould not ſhoote of, but <hi>30.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12662:13"/>
ſhot à peece euery day, and that in the preſence of the Captaines, who were ſtill preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſoldiers and Gunners ſhould not ſhoote of in vaine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>29.</hi> of May there came towardes vs from <hi>Candia</hi> à <hi>Fregat</hi> or Pinniſſe, the which geuing vs great hope and lightening of ayde, encreaſed maruelouſly euery mans courage. The Turkes with great trauell and ſlaughter of both ſides, had wonne at the laſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcharfe from vs, with great reſiſtance and mortalitie on both partes. Wherupon they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan on the other ſide of the fift battery to fill vp the ditch, with the earth that they threwe downe, which was taken neare the wall of the Counterſcharfe. But all that earth and falling downe of the wall made by the ſhot of their artilary, was caryed away of vs within the Citie, all our company labouring continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as well by night as day, vntill our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had made certaine loope holes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wall, through the which they fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cking and ſcouring all the ditch with their Harquebuſſie, ſtopped our former courſe of carying, or going that way any more, without certaine and expreſſe daunger. But <hi>M. Giouanni Marmori,</hi> à fortifier, had deuiſed à certain kinde of ioyned boordes, the which being caried of the ſoldiers, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhot of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Harquebuſers, ſo that ſome other quantitie of earth, but no great ſtore, was caried alſo away: in the which place this foreſayd fortifier was ſlaine, who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12662:13"/>
had done eſpeciall good ſeruice in all our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary affaires. And our enemies hauing caſt ſo much earth into the ditch, as filled it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and made it à firme way to the wall of the Counterſcharfe, and caſting before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth by little and little, they made one Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe euen vnto the wall on two ſides in all their batteries, the which they made thicke and ſtronge with Wolpackes, and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots, to aſſure them ſelues the better of our flanckers.</p>
            <p>When they had once poſſeſſed the ditch, that they coulde not bee hurt of vs but by chaunce, they began forthwith to caſt &amp; digge out vndermines to vndermine the Brey, the Turret of <hi>S. Nappa,</hi> the Commaunder of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druzzi,</hi> the Keepe of <hi>Campo Santo,</hi> the Cortain, and the Turrion of the <hi>Arſenall:</hi> ſo that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able no longer to ſerue our turne and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye thoſe fewe flanckers, we threw downe wildefire into our enemies campe, the which annoyed them very ſore, becauſe it fired their Wolpackes, and alſo their Fagots. And for the better encouragement of the ſoldiers, the right honourable <hi>Bragadino</hi> gaue to euery ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier one Duckat, the which could gaine or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer any of the former Wollpackes, making cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>termines in all places. To y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which charge <hi>Maggio</hi> the fortifier knight was appointed, who in all our buſines ſerued with ſuch dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and courage, as he was able, or was requiſite. But the countermines mette not,
<pb facs="tcp:12662:14"/>
ſauing thoſe of the Commaunder of <hi>S. Nappa,</hi> of <hi>Andruzzi,</hi> and that of <hi>Campo Santo,</hi> becauſe they were open, and our men ſallied out often both by day and night into the ditch to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue better the way of the mines, and to fire the Fagots and Wooll. Nor we ceaſſed at any time through the vnſpeakeable trauell of the Lord <hi>Baglione</hi> (who had the ouerſight of all theſe matters) to trouble our enemies intents, by all maner of wit and policie, deuiding the companies for the batteries, ioyning and pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in all places à gariſon of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Albanois</hi> ſoldiers, ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Albania, otherwiſe called Epirus, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſerue the Venetians, both on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe and foot, very ſkilful and painfull.</note> 
               <hi>Albanois</hi> ſoldiers, who as well on foote as on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, ſhewed alwayes notable courage and manhoode.</p>
            <div n="1" type="assault">
               <head>¶ The firſt Aſſault.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>21.</hi> of Iune, they put fire to the mine of the Turret of the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> wheras <hi>Giambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat Bey</hi> toke charge, who with great ruine rent in ſunder à moſt great and thicke wall, and ſo opened the ſame, that he threw downe more then halfe therof, breaking alſo one part of the baymure, made before to vpholde the aſſault. And ſodainly à great number of the Turkes ſkipping vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ruines therof, diſplayed their Enſignes, euen to the toppe of the ſame. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Pietro Conte</hi> with his company, was in that warde, the which was much ſhaken and terrified by that ſodaine ruine. I with my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany came firſt thether, ſo that they ſhortly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12662:14"/>
tooke the repulſe, and although they refreſhed them ſelues with new ſupplyes <hi>5.</hi> or <hi>6.</hi> times, yet they failed of their purpoſe.<note place="margin">Of this noble and painfull Venetian Gentleman <hi>M. Gio. Anto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nio Querini</hi> (who was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward hewen in ſunder by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Mustafà</hi>) I was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained very courteouſly in my trauell at <hi>Corſyra,</hi> now called <hi>Corfù,</hi> he being then there <hi>Mag. Castellano</hi> or Captaine of one of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels.</note> There fought perſonally the <hi>L. Baglione: Bragadino</hi> and <hi>Querini</hi> being armed, ſtoode not farre of to refreſh and comfort our ſoldiers, and the Captaine of the Caſtell with the Ordinance, that was planted vpon the Buttereis, deſtroyed many of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, when they gaue the aſſault, the which endured <hi>5.</hi> houres together: ſo that of Turkes were ſlain very many, and of our ſide betwixt them that were ſlaine and hurt à <hi>100:</hi> Moſt part of the which number were caſt away by à miſchaunce of our wildefire, the which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnaduiſedly &amp; negligently handled, burnt vp many of our owne company. There died at that preſent the Earle <hi>Gio. Franceſco Goro,</hi> the Captaine <hi>Barnardino Agubio:</hi> and by the throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſtones <hi>Hercole Malatesta,</hi> Captaine <hi>Pietro Conte,</hi> with other Captaines and Standerd-bearers were very ſore hurt.</p>
               <p>The night following arriued in <hi>Cyprus</hi> à Pinniſſe from <hi>Candia,</hi> which bringing newes of moſt certaine ayde, greatly encreaſed both the mirth and courage of vs all, ſo that we made ſoone after, with the helpe of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Marco Criuellatore,</hi> and <hi>Maggio</hi> the knight, certaine retreates flancked to all the places beaten downe, and where as they ſuſpected that the enemie had digged vp any mines, with Hogſheades, Cheſtes, Tykes, &amp; Sackes ſtuffed full of moyſt earth (the Grecians with
<pb facs="tcp:12662:15"/>
all ſpeede hauing already brought almoſt all that which they had) becauſe they hauing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched their Canueis about neceſſary vſes,<note place="margin">In extremities men haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to ſpare trifles.</note> they brought their hanginges, cortaines, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, euen to their very ſheetes, to make and ſtuffe vp their foreſaid ſackes, à very good and ready way to make vp again their vaymures, the which were throwen downe with the fury of the artilary, which neuer ſtinted, ſo that we made vp againe ſtill that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, the which was throwen downe and broken in the day, ſleeping very ſeldome:<note place="margin">Prouident and carefull gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſeldome ſleepe all the night at any time, much leſſe in daungerous ſeaſons.</note> all the ſoldiers ſtanding alwayes vpon the walles, viſited continually of the Gouerners of the Citie, which ſlept at no time, but in the extreme heate of the day, hauing no other time to take their reſt, becauſe the enemie was at hand, geuing vs continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Alarmes, not ſuffering vs long to breath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="assault">
               <head>¶ The ſecond Aſſault.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>29.</hi> of the ſame moneth, they ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mine made towardes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Brey on fire, the which mine was digged in ſtone, which brake and cleft all thinges in peeces, and cauſed great ruine, making an eaſie way for the enemye to aſſault vs, who with an outragious fury came to the toppe, whereas <hi>Mustafà</hi> their Generall was altogether preſent,<note place="margin">A ſmall thing at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, or in due time done, helpeth much.</note> which aſſault was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, and ſtayed at the beginning of the Earle <hi>Hercole Martinengo</hi> with his gariſon, and ſo were repulſed by our company, who fought
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12662:15"/>
without any aduauntage of couert, the vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure being throwen downe by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mine. There were ſlaine of our company Captaine <hi>Meani</hi> the <hi>Sargent Maior</hi> of our armye, Captaine <hi>Celio de Fuochi,</hi> Captaine <hi>Eraſmo da Fermo:</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Soldatello, Antonio d' Aſcoli,</hi> Captaine <hi>Gio. d' Istria,</hi> Standerdbearers, with many other officers, were ſore wounded, there dyed alſo <hi>30.</hi> other of our common ſoldiers. At the Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall they were beaten backe with greater da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of our enemies, and ſmall hurt to vs. Fiue onely of our part being ſlain there, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Captaine <hi>Giacomo da Fabriano</hi> dyed, and I was wounded in my left legge with an Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuſe ſhot. The which aſſault continued <hi>6.</hi> houres, the Biſhop of <hi>Limiſſo</hi> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vp there, encouraging the ſoldiers.<note place="margin">That certaine women inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Iland be <hi>Viragos,</hi> or mankinde, I ſawe ſufficient triall at my laſt being there, in a Citie called <hi>Saline.</hi>
                  </note> Where alſo were found preſent ſtoute women, who came the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with weapons, ſtones, &amp; water, to helpe the ſoldiers. Our enemies vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding how great hinderance they had receaued at theſe two aſſaultes, chaunged their mindes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan againe with greater furye then euer they had before accuſtomed to lay battery to all places, and into our retreates, ſo that they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring more ſpedely then euer they did, made <hi>7.</hi> other forts more, vnder the Caſtell, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the artilary fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them which were farther of, planting of it ſomewhat nearer to the number of <hi>80.</hi> they battered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holde with ſo great rage, that on the <hi>8.</hi> of Iuly, with the ſame night alſo, was numbred <hi>5000.</hi> Cannon
<pb facs="tcp:12662:16"/>
ſhot, and after that ſort they ouerthrewe to the ground y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vaymures, that ſcarcely with great trauell and paine we could repayre them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, becauſe our men that laboured about them were continually ſlaine by their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and by reaſon of the endleſſe tempeſt of the ſhot of their Harquebuſers. And our men began to decreaſe. For the Turkes cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs to retyre from our Breyes, by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of their artilary and mining in ſuch ſort, that there being no more ſtanding left for our ſoldiers, becauſe we making our vaymures more thicke, our ſtanding began to waxe nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, the which preſently we of neceſſitie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged with boordes as à ſcaffolde to the vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, whereby we might haue more elbow roome to fight.<note place="margin">It is accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſhift, to leaue that to our enemies with hindrance, which we can not any longer keepe, and vſe to our owne commoditie.</note> Captaine <hi>Maggio</hi> alſo made one mine vnder the ſayd Brey, to the entent, that we being not able any longer to keepe it, the ſame might bee left to our enemies to their great hinderaunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="assault">
               <head>¶ The third Aſſault.</head>
               <p>TO the ſayd Brey the <hi>9.</hi> of Iuly, they gaue the third aſſault, to the Turrion of <hi>Santa Nappa,</hi> to that of <hi>Andruzzi,</hi> to the Cortaine, to the Keepe of the Arſenall: the which aſſault hauing continued more then <hi>6.</hi> houres, they were beaten backe in <hi>4.</hi> places, but we left the Brey to their great loſſe, and ours alſo: becauſe we being aſſaulted, our company be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12662:16"/>
not able to manneage their Pikes in good order, by reaſon of the narrownes of the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding where they were, being willing to retyre in that order, as the <hi>L. Baglione</hi> had preſcribed vnto them, and could not, caſt them ſelues at the laſt into à confuſe order, and retyred, they being mingled amongeſt the Turkes: ſo that fire being geuen to our mine, the which (with à terrible ſight to beholde) ſlewe preſently of our enemies more then à <hi>1000.</hi> and aboue à <hi>100.</hi> of vs. There dyed Captaine <hi>Roberto Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uezzi,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Marchetto da Fermo</hi> was greuouſly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. At the aſſault of the Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dyed Captaine <hi>Dauid Noce</hi> maſter of the Campe, and I my ſelfe was hurt by the racing of à Cannon ſhot. This aſſault continued fiue houres, and the Citizens of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> ſhewed great courage in euery place, with their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alſo, and young ſtriplinges. The Brey was ſo defaced by reaſon of this mine ſet on fire, that no body any more attempted to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſame: becauſe there was no apt place remayning to ſtay vpon. The left flancker onely remained ſtill, whereas an other mine was made. The gate of <hi>Limiſſo</hi> was ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this foreſayd Brey, &amp; ſomewhat lower, which was alwayes open, hauing made to the ſame à Portall, with à Percollois annexed to it, the which Percollois by the cutting of à ſmall corde, was à preſent defence to the gate, and our ſoldiers gaue their atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance by that gate to bring in the battered earth, which fell
<pb facs="tcp:12662:17"/>
in the ditches from the rampayre: and when they ſaw that their enemies in <hi>4.</hi> dayes came not thether, they began to entrench aboue the Brey, and by the flanckers aboue they ſuffered no perſon to paſſe out of the gate, the which thing brought great ſuſpition vnto our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, becauſe they were oft times aſſailed of our company.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="assault">
               <head>¶ The fourth Aſſault.</head>
               <p>WHerefore they came the <hi>14.</hi> day of Iuly to aſſault the gate of <hi>Limiſſo,</hi> and lying their battery to all other places, they came and planted their Auncientes euen before the gate, wheras the <hi>L. Baglione,</hi> and <hi>Sig. Luigi</hi> were in readineſſe, who had taken vpon them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that gate of the Citie. Who as ſoone as they had encouraged their ſoldiers, ſallying ſwiftly forth, killed, and put to flight the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of them, and at the laſt geuing fire to the mine of the flancker ſlewe <hi>400.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine at daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous times not onely much comforteth the common ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth greatly his credite and commendation with all men.</note> Turkes, and <hi>Sig. Baglione</hi> at the ſame time wonne an Auncient of our enemies, wraſting it violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of one of the Auncientbearers handes. The day following they gaue fire to the mine of the Cortaine, the which thing not falling out greatly to their purpoſe, they followed not their prepared aſſault. Wherefore they began to fortifie, and aduaunce hyer their Trauerſes in the ditches, for their better aſſuraunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt they ſhould geue the aſſault: and they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12662:17"/>
had emptied and caryed away all the earth neare vnto the Counterſcharfe, where they lodged in their pauilions, ſo that we could not deſcrie them. They ſhot <hi>7.</hi> peeces of artilary vpon the wall of the Counterſcharfe ſo couert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they were not ſeene: two fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Brey of the Turrion of <hi>Santa Nappa,</hi> one from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druzzi,</hi> and two other all à long the battery of the Cortaine. And they came with certaine boordes couered with raw and greene hydes, vnder which they brought their men to digge in the vaymures, we being nothing behind or forgetfull to caſt wildefire amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt them, and ſometime to iſſue forth of our ſallies called Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns, to offend their Pioners, although to our great hinderaunce. And we ſtill repayred the vaymures by all meanes poſſible, with Buffe ſkinnes, being moyſt and weet, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in alſo earth, ſhredes, and cotton with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being well bound together with cordes: all the women of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> gathering them ſelues together in companyes in euery ſtreete (being guided of one of their Prieſtes called <hi>Caloiero</hi>) reſorted dayly to à certaine place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, to labour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caloiero</hi> be ſecular Greek prieſtes, who by their lawes may be, and commonly are alſo maried.</note> gathering and prouiding for the ſoldiers, ſtones and water, the which was kept for all aſſaultes in halfe butts to quench the fire, which the Turkes threwe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt them.</p>
               <p>They hauing had no great ſucceſſe in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the gate, they found out à new way, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of before, in gathering together à
<pb facs="tcp:12662:18"/>
great qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie of certaine wood called <hi>Teglia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Teglia</hi> in Latin called <hi>Teda,</hi> is a certaine wood, which burneth eaſily, and ſauoureth vnpleaſantly, of the which there is great ſtore in Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia: ſometime it is vſed for a Torche.</note> which eaſely burned, and ſmelt very euill, the which they throwing before the former gate of the Citie, and Fagots faſtened to the ſame, with certaine beames beſmered with Pitch, kindled ſodainly ſo great à fire, as was not poſſible for vs to quench the ſame, although we threw vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it whole Buts of water, which were throwen downe from an high Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which Buts preſently brake in ſunder. Thys fire continued <hi>4.</hi> dayes, wherefore we were enforced by reaſon of the extreme heate and ſtinche, to withdraw our ſelues farther inward, and they deſcending towardes their lower flanckers, beganne other mines, ſo that the gate was ſhut vp, becauſe it could be no longer kept open,<note place="margin">No neceſſary thing to be done was left vnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part.</note> and ſodainly (à thing mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous to be ſpoken) the ſtanding of the Brey being repayred and made vp againe, they pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one peece ouer againſt the gate, the which of vs with ſtones, earth, and other thinges, was ſodainly buried vp. By thys time we were driuen to an exigent, all our prouiſion within the Citie ſtooping very lowe, ſauing onely hope,<note place="margin">Mans courage oft abateth, but hope ſeldome forſaketh.</note> the noble courage of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Captaines, and the ſtoute readines of the ſoldiers: our wine, and fleſhe as well poudered as vnpoudered was ſpent, nor there was any Cheeſe to be gotten, but vpon an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable price, our company hauing eaten vp their Horſe,<note place="margin">Saguntina fames.</note> Aſſes, and Cattes, for lacke of other victualls: there was nothing left to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12662:18"/>
eaten, but à ſmall quantitie of bread, and Beanes, and we dranke water and Vineger together, whereof was not much left, when that we perceaued that our enemies had dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and caſt vp <hi>3.</hi> mines in the Commaunder of the gate, they labouring in all places more diligently then euer they did before, bringing into the ditch, ouer agaynſt the battery of the Cortaine, à hill of earth, as high as the wall: And already they came to the wall aboue the Counterſcharfe ouer againſt the Turrion of the Arſenall, and had made one Commaunder complete, fenced with ſhares, like vnto plough ſhares, in proportion and height correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to ours.</p>
               <p>Within the Citie were remaining but <hi>500.</hi> Italian ſoldiers, who were not hurt, yet very faint and wery by their long watching and paines in fighting in thoſe feruent &amp; burning heates, which are in thoſe partes.<note place="margin">In Iuly the heate is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme in this Iland, that the inhabitauntes thereof, are not wont to trauel, but by night onely.</note> And the greater and better part alſo of the Grecians were by thys time ſlaine, when as the cheefe of thoſe Citizens remayning, did fully reſolue them ſelues (the which was about the <hi>20.</hi> of Iuly) to preſent à ſupplication in writing to that noble gentleman <hi>Bragadino <hi>Proueditore,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">A letter or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priottes vnto <hi>Sig. Bragadino.</hi>
                  </note> deſiring and beſeeching him, that ſeing their Citie &amp; fortreſſe was thus battered &amp; brought to extremitie, without ſufficient ayde to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſame, without ſubſtaunce or ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, hauing no hope of ſuccour, or any new ſupply, they hauing ſpent and conſumed not
<pb facs="tcp:12662:19"/>
onely their goods, but alſo their liues for the defence of them, and in teſtifying of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſeruice towardes the noble and royall ſtate of the Segniory of Venice, that it might now pleaſe him, and the reſt of the honourable Gouernours, that were preſent, &amp; put in truſt, hauing à carefull eye vnto ſome honourable conditions, to haue now at the laſt à reſpect to the credite and honour of their long trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wifes, and the ſafegarde of their poore chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which otherwiſe were ſhortly very like to be à pray to their bloudthirſting and raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning enemies.<note place="margin">The aunſwere of the former letter.</note> To the which letter or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication ſpeedy aunſwere was made by the forenamed honourable <hi>Bragadino,</hi> comforting them, that they ſhould by no meanes abate their courage, and that ſhortly he looked for ſuccour from the Segniorye, diminiſhing as much as he might, the feare which they had conceaued in their hartes, diſpatching and ſending away ſodainly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Cyprus</hi> into <hi>Candia</hi> à Pinniſſe to certifie the Duke and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours there, in what extremitie they were. The Turkes by thys tyme had ended their mines, and ſet them on fire, the <hi>29.</hi> of Iuly, in the which ſpace our men according as they were wonte to doe, renued &amp; made vp againe the vaymures ruined before by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ordinance, and hauing no other ſtuffe left to aduaunce them with,<note place="margin">It ſtandeth with reaſon, in hope of ſauing the greater, to let the leſſer go.</note> made ſackes of Carſey, vnto the which the noble <hi>Tiepolo</hi> diligently looked. The <hi>3.</hi> mines of the Commaunder did great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12662:19"/>
to vs, hauing throwen downe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the earth, whereas the Gouernour <hi>Randacchi</hi> was ſlaine. The mine of the Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ouerthrew all the reſt of the Turrion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſmouldered and choked one whole gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our ſoldiers, the <hi>2.</hi> flanckers onely ſtill remayning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="assault">
               <head>¶ The fifth Aſſault.</head>
               <p>THe enemies trauelled much to become maiſters of thoſe foreſayd flanckers, and to ſallye forth by the other batteries, and thys aſſault laſted from three of the clocke in the after noone vntill night, where, and at what tyme were ſlaine very many of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemes. In thys aſſault <hi>Sig. Giacomo Strambali</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the reſt, ſhewed much worthineſſe, as he had done before in other conflictes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="assault">
               <head>¶ The 6. and laſt Aſſault.</head>
               <p>THe next morning following, at the breake of the day, they aſſailed all places, the whiche Aſſault continued more then ſixe houres, with very little hurt on our ſide, becauſe our enemies fought more coldly then they were wont to doe, annoying of vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually on the Sea ſide with their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, ſhooting in all theyr Aſſaultes and batteries continually Cannon ſhotte in all partes of the Citie, as neare as they might.
<pb facs="tcp:12662:20"/>
After we had defended and repulſed this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, and perceaued thinges brought to à nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower ſtraite then they were wont to be at,<note place="margin">Neceſſitie oft times preſſeth vs in the end to that, which our will continually ſpurneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</note> we hauing left in all the whole Citie, but <hi>7.</hi> barrels of pouder, the Gouernours of the Citie fully determined to yelde vp them ſelues and the Citie, with honourable conditions. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt of Auguſt in the after noone, they tooke à truce, one being come for that purpoſe from <hi>Mustafà</hi> the Generall, with whom they concluded the next morning following to geue <hi>2.</hi> hoſtages à peece, vntill ſuch time as both armies were agreed. For our hoſtages (by the appointment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right honourable <hi>Bragadino</hi>) were ſent forth the Earle <hi>Hercole Martinengo,</hi> and <hi>Sig. Matteo Colſi</hi> à Citizen of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our enemies came into the Citie the Liefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of <hi>Muſtafà,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Giannezzeri</hi> be the Garde of the great Turke, ſo that <hi>Agà de' Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annizzeri</hi> is the Captaine of the Turkes Garde.</note> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Agà</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Giannizzers,</hi> the which were met, euen vnto the gate of the Citie, of <hi>Sig. Baglione</hi> with <hi>200.</hi> Harquebuſers: ours alſo were met in like maner with great pompe with horſemen &amp; Harquebuſers, with the ſonne alſo of <hi>Muſtafà</hi> in perſon, who made very much of them.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Baglione</hi> imparld with theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtages, which were then come for that purpoſe of the articles of peace, requiring by them of their Generall, their liues, armour, and goods, <hi>5.</hi> peeces of Ordinance, <hi>3.</hi> of the beſt horſes, and ſafe paſſage from thence vnto <hi>Candia</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with their Gallies, and laſt of all, that the Grecians inhabiting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iland might
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12662:20"/>
dwell there ſtill quietly, and enioye peaceably their owne goods and poſſeſſions, liuing ſtill Chriſtians hereafter, as they had done before. All the which requeſtes and articles were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon, graunted,<note place="margin">Iuſt Turkiſhe dealing, to ſpeake and not to meane: ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and neuer to performe the ſame.</note> and ſubſcribed vnto by the hand of <hi>Muſtafà.</hi> Forthwith were ſent Gallies, and other veſſels into the hauen, ſo that our ſoldiers immediately beganne to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barke them ſelues, of the which the greater part were already gone aboorde, the nobilitie and our cheefe Captaines alſo being likewiſe very deſirous to depart. The <hi>15.</hi> of Auguſt in the morning, the worthy <hi>Bragadino</hi> ſent me with à letter vnto <hi>Muſtafà,</hi> by the which he ſignified, that the ſame night he would come vnto him to deliuer vp the keyes of the Citie, and that he would leaue in the holde the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable gentleman <hi>Tiepolo,</hi> praying him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that whileſt he ſhould haue iuſt cauſe thus to be abroad, that there might be no harme done at home, and in the Citie. The Turkes from our truce taking vntill that time, practiſed with vs all familiarly,<note place="margin">The Wolfe ſometime cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiteth the voice of the Goate, and the deceat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth plaine and vpright dealing, that he may the ſooner intrappe the ſimple.</note> &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuſpition of ſiniſter or double dealing, they hauing ſhewed vs much courteſie both in worde and deede. <hi>Muſtafà</hi> him ſelfe by worde of mouth preſently aunſwered me to thys let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in this ſort, that I ſhould returne, &amp; make relation to this noble man <hi>Bragadino,</hi> who had ſent me, that he ſhould come ouer to him at his owne pleaſure, for he was very deſirous both to ſee and know him, for hys great worthines
<pb facs="tcp:12662:21"/>
and prowes, that he had tryed to be in hym, and in the other of his Captaines and ſoldiers, of whoſe manhoode and courage he would honourably report, where ſoeuer he came, as occaſion ſhould ſerue therunto: and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that he ſhould nothing doubt of any thing:<note place="margin">But full euill may the ſimple Lambes truſt the rauening Wolfe.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in no maner of condition he would ſuffer any violence to be done to thoſe, which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned behinde within the Citie. So I ſpeedely returning, made true report of the ſame: and towardes night about <hi>4.</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clocke, the right honourable <hi>Bragadino</hi> accompanied with the <hi>L. Baglione,</hi> with <hi>Sig. Aluigi Martinengo,</hi> with the right worſhipfull <hi>Sig. Gio. Antonio Querini,</hi> with the right worſhipfull <hi>Sig. Andrea Bragadino,</hi> with the Knight of <hi>Haſte,</hi> with the Captaine <hi>Carlo Ragonaſco,</hi> with Captaine <hi>Franceſco Straco,</hi> with Captaine <hi>Hector</hi> of <hi>Breſcia,</hi> with Captaine <hi>Giro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomo di Sacile,</hi> and with other gentlemen, and <hi>50.</hi> ſoldiers: the Gouernours and noble men with their ſwordes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoldiers with their Harquebuſers, came forth of their holde, and went vnto the Pauilion of <hi>Muſtafà,</hi> of whom, all they at the beginning, were courteouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, and cauſed to ſit down by him, he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning and diſcourſing with them of diuers thinges, à certaine time: and drawing them from one matter to an other, at the laſt vpon à ſodaine picked à quarell vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">An eaſie thing it is to finde a ſtaffe to beate a dogge: and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is an ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, then none at all.</note> eſpecially burthening that noble <hi>Bragadino</hi> with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, laying to his charge, that he had cauſed certaine of his ſlaues in the time that the truce
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12662:21"/>
continued betwixt them, to be put to death. The which thing was moſt falſe. So that he being angry therewith ſodainly ſtept forth, and commaunded them to be bound. Thus they being vnarmed (not ſuffered at that time to enter into hys Pauilion, with their former weapons) and bound, were lead one by one into the market place, before hys Pauilion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſently cutte and hewen in ſunder in hys preſence, and laſt of all from that worthy and noble <hi>Bragadino</hi> (who being bound as the reſt, and being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded twiſe or thriſe to ſtretch forth his necke,<note place="margin">The propertie of true forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is, not to be broken with ſodaine terrors.</note> as though he ſhould haue bene beheaded, the which moſt boldly he did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſparke of feare) hys eares were cut of, and cauſing him to be ſtretched out moſt vilely vpon the ground, <hi>Muſtafà</hi> talking with hym, and blaſpheming the holy name of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, demaunding hym,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mustafà,</hi> coſin germaine to the theefe, which honge on the left ſide of our Sauiour at his Paſſion.</note> where is now thy Chriſt, that he helpeth thee not: To all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which no aunſwere at all was geuen of that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gentleman. The Earle <hi>Hercole Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nengo,</hi> which was ſent for one of the hoſtages, who was alſo bound, was hidden by one of <hi>Muſtafàs</hi> Eunukes vntill ſuch time as hys fury was paſt, afterward hys life being graunted hym, he was made the Eunukes ſlaue. Three Grecians which were vnder his Pauilion were left vntouched. All the ſoldiers which were found in the campe, and all ſortes of Chriſtians to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of <hi>300.</hi> were ſodainly ſlaine, they nothing miſtruſting any ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb facs="tcp:12662:22"/>
or tyranny. The Chriſtian ſoldiers, which were imbarcked à little before, were lincked and fettered with yron chaines, made ſlaues, all thinges being taken from them, and ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into their ſhirtes.</p>
               <p>The ſecond day after thys murther was committed, which was the <hi>17.</hi> of Auguſt, <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtafà</hi> entred the firſt time into the Citie, and cauſed the valiant and wiſe gouernor<note n="*" place="margin">With this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice <hi>M. Lorenzo Tiepolo,</hi> now thus vilely put to death, in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople into Chriſtendome, I ſayled <hi>300.</hi> miles, namely, from <hi>Candia</hi> or <hi>Creta,</hi> vnto <hi>Zacyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos,</hi> now called: <hi>Zanthe,</hi> with his great fauour: he being then, as at this ſeege alſo he was Captain and Gouernour of <hi>Baffo.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tiepolo</hi> to be hanged, who remayned behinde, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the returne of <hi>Sig. Bragadino.</hi> I being in the citie at that preſent, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other of my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were thus miſerably ſlaine &amp; made ſlaues, hid my ſelfe in certaine of the Grecians houſes the ſpace of <hi>5.</hi> daies, and they not being able to keepe me in couert any longer for feare of the great penaltie, which was proclamed againſt ſuch tranſgreſſours and concealers, I offered, and gaue my ſelfe ſlaue to one <hi>Sangaccho del Bir,</hi> promiſing hym <hi>500.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zechini,</hi> be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine peeces of fine golde coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Venice: euery one of the which is in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue vj. ſhillinges viij. pence of our money and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what better: and equall alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſhe <hi>Byraltom.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Zechins</hi> for my rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome, with whom I remained in the campe. The Friday following (being the Turkes ſabboth day) thys worthy and pacient gentleman <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadino</hi> was led ſtill in the preſence of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull tyrant <hi>Muſtafà,</hi> to the batteries made vnto the Citie, whereas he being compelled to carrye two baſkets of earth, the one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hys backe, the other in hys hand ſlaue like, to euery ſundry battery, being enforced alſo to kiſſe the ground as oft as he paſſed by him, was afterward brought vnto the Sea ſide, where he being placed in à chaire to leane
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12662:22"/>
and ſtay vpon, was winched vp in that chaire, and faſtened vnto the Maineyarde of à Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and hoyſted vp with à Crane, to ſhew him to all the Chriſtian ſoldiers and ſlaues (which were in the hauen already ſhipped) he being afterward let down, and brought to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place, the tormentors tooke of hys clothes from hym, and tacked hym vnto the Pillary, whereas he was moſt cruelly fleyed quicke: with ſo great conſtancie and faith on his part, that he neuer loſt or abated any iotte of hys ſtedfaſt courage, being ſo farre from any fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,<note place="margin">His death an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his former life.</note> that he at that preſent with moſt ſtoute hart reproched them, and ſpake much ſhame of hys moſt trayterous dealing in breaking of hys faythfull promiſe. At the laſt without any kinde of alteration of hys conſtancye, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending hys ſoule vnto almighty God, gaue vp the goſte. When he had thus ended hys life (thankes be to God) hys ſkinne being taken and filled with ſtraw, was commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded forthwith to be hanged vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bowſprit of a<note n="*" place="margin">A Foyſte is as it were a Briga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, being ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what larger then halfe a Galley, much vſed of the Turkiſh <hi>Curſaros,</hi> or as we call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pirates, or Rouers.</note> Foyſte, and to be caryed alongſt the coaſt of <hi>Syria</hi> by the ſea ſide, that all the port townes might ſee, and vnderſtand who he was.</p>
               <p>Thys is now ſo much as I am able to declare to your highnes by that I ſawe my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Thinges ſeene are of much more credite, the onely heard.</note> and can remember whileſt that I was in the Fortreſſe: that alſo, which by true rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others I could vnderſtand, and ſaw alſo my ſelfe in the Campe, whileſt I was ſlaue, I will likewiſe breefly vtter vnto you.
<pb facs="tcp:12662:23"/>
The enemies armies was in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber <hi>200.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Turkes call all thoſe Segni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ories which they haue in <hi>Aſia,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly by the name of <hi>Natolia,</hi> as they do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe terme it to be in <hi>Grecia,</hi> what ſoeuer is in any part of <hi>Europe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder the great Turke.</note> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons of all ſortes and qualities. Of ſoldiers which toke paye there were <hi>80.</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, beſides the which number, there were <hi>14.</hi> thouſand of <hi>Giannizzers</hi> taken out from all the holdes of <hi>Syria, Caramania, Natolia,</hi> and part of them alſo which came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<note n="*" place="margin">The Gate of the great Turke, is as much to ſay, as Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople: the which they call in the Turkiſhe language, <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boll.</hi>
                  </note> Gate of the great Turke. The venturers with the ſword were <hi>60.</hi> thouſand in number. The reaſon, why there were ſo many of this ſort, was becauſe <hi>Muſtafà</hi> had diſperſed à rumour, through the Turkes dominion, that <hi>Famagoſta</hi> was much more wealthy and riche, then the Citie of <hi>Nicoſia</hi> was: ſo for that cauſe, and by the commodious and eaſie paſſage from <hi>Syria</hi> ouer into <hi>Cyprus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gli <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enturieri da ſpada,</hi> are a kinde of venturing ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are wont to follow the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye in hope of the ſpoyle.</note> theſe venturers were eaſily induced to come thether. In <hi>75.</hi> dayes (all the which time the battery ſtill continued) <hi>140.</hi> thouſand yron pellets were ſhot of, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aleppo,</hi> a famous Citie neare vnto <hi>Antiochia,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called in Greke, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Citie of the Sunne.</note> and ſeene. The cheefe perſonages which were in their armye neare vnto <hi>Muſtafà,</hi> were theſe following: the <hi>Baſſà</hi> of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> the <hi>Baſſà</hi> of <hi>Natolia, <hi>Muſafer</hi> Baſſà</hi> of <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> the <hi>Baſſà</hi> of <hi>Caramania,</hi> the <hi>Agà</hi> of the <hi>Giannizzers, <hi>Giambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bey</hi> in the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſhe language, ſignifieth knight with vs.</note> 
                  <hi>Bey,</hi> the <hi>Sangiaccho</hi> of <hi>Tripolis,</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Begliarbei</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth L. Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> 
                  <hi>Begliar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bei</hi> of Greece, the <hi>Baſſà</hi> of <hi>Sciuaſſi</hi> &amp; of <hi>Maraſco, <hi>Ferca Framburaro,</hi>
                  </hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sangaccho,</hi> is that perſon with the Turkes, that gouerneth a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</note> 
                  <hi>Sangaccho</hi> of <hi>Antipo, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman Bey,</hi>
                  </hi> three <hi>Sangacchos</hi> of <hi>Arabia, <hi>Muſtafà Bey</hi>
                  </hi> Generall of the Venturers, <hi>Fergat</hi> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Malathia,</hi> the <hi>Framburaro</hi> of <hi>Diuerie,</hi> the <hi>Sangaccho</hi> of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and other <hi>Sangacchos</hi> of leſſer credite, with the number of <hi>80.</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12662:23"/>
perſons beſides, as by the muſter made by his commiſſion might well appeare.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Framburaro</hi> which was at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> was appoynted and left gouernour at <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta,</hi> and the report was that there ſhould be left in all the Iland of <hi>Cyprus 20.</hi> thouſand perſons, with <hi>2000.</hi> horſe, many of the which I ſaw, being very leane and euill appoynted for ſeruice. It ſeemeth alſo à thing not imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the matter, to ſignifie to you,<note place="margin">God ſuffereth much to be done to his ſeruants, but neuer forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them.</note> how I by the eſpeciall grace of God, was deliuered out of their cruell handes, I hauing payed within <hi>42.</hi> dayes (all the which time I was ſlaue) <hi>500. Zechins</hi> for my raunſome to hym, whoſe priſoner I was, by the meanes of the <hi>Conſul</hi> for the French Marchantes, à ligger then at <hi>Tripolis,</hi> who à little before came from <hi>Tripolis</hi> in <hi>Syria</hi> vnto <hi>Cyprus,</hi> into the Turkes campe. Yet for all that I had payed thys ſumme of money to him, he would not ſo ſet me at libertie, but feeding me vp ſtill with faire words, and promiſing me, that he would firſt bring me vnto his gouernment, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butted vpon à peece of the famous riuer of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and afterward dimiſſe me. The which malice and falſehoode of hys I percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, determined with my ſelfe to geue hym the ſlippe, and to flye: ſo I wayting my time, and repayring often to the Citie, at length met with à ſmall Fiſher bote, of the which à poore Grecian was honor &amp; maiſter, with whom in one night with two onely Ores and à ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:12662:24"/>
ſaile made of two ſhirtes,<note place="margin">Neceſſitie oft times ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth mens wits, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth boldnes.</note> paſſed ouer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> vnto <hi>Tripolis,</hi> being in very great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of drowning, whereas I remained in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert in the houſe of certaine Chriſtians, vntill the <hi>25.</hi> of September, at what time I depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thence in à little French ſhip called <hi>Santo Vittor,</hi> which came into theſe partes, and as we rode, we touched at à part of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> weſtward, called <hi>Capo delle Gatte,</hi> where as I came à land, and talking with certaine of the inhabitaunce of the villages, who were then by chaunce à hauking, demaunded of them, how they were intreated of the Turkes, and after what ſort the Iland was tylled: to the which they aunſwered, that they could not poſſibly be in worſe pickle, then they were at that preſent, not enioying that quietly, which was their owne, being made villans &amp; flaues, and almoſt alwayes carying away the <hi>Baſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nados,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The nature of euery commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie is ſooner vnderſtoode by lacking, then by continuall enioying of the ſame.</note> ſo that now (they ſayd) they knew by triall too perfectly the pleſaunt and peaceable gouernment of the Chriſtians, wiſhing and praying God that they might ſhortly returne. And concerning the tyllage of the Iland they made aunſwere moreouer, that no part of it was plowed or laboured, ſauing onely that mountaine, which was towardes the Weſt, and that becauſe they were little troubled with the crueltie of the Turkes, but as for the plaine and Eaſt part of the Iland, there was ſmall ſeede ſowen therein, but became in à maner deſert, there being left but fewe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12662:24"/>
and leſſe ſtore of cattell there. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward we departing from thence, arriued in<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Candia,</hi> of the olde writers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Creta</hi> in latin, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Greke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had once a <hi>100.</hi> Cities in it, now there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>4.</hi> thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly named, <hi>Candia, La Cania, Retimo,</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Candia,</hi> I for my part being clothed in Sackcloth, whereas ſoone after by the great courteſie of the right honourable <hi>Sig. Latino Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſino,</hi> I was new apparelled accordingly, frendly welcomed, and my neceſſitie relieued. From whence I ſhortly after ſailing in à Cypriottes ſhip (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God) arriued in this Citie in health, and am ſafely come<note n="†" place="margin">It is great pleaſure for any true ſubiect, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long trauell, to ſee the ſmoke of his natiue Countrey.</note> home now at the honourable feete of your highneſſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="lists_of_casualties">
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:25"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Captaines of the Chriſtians dead in Famagoſta.</head>
               <item>THe Lord <hi>Estor Baglione.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thr Lord <hi>Aluigi Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nengo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Federico Baglione.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Knight of <hi>Aſta</hi> Vicegouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Dauid Noce</hi> Maiſter of the Campe.</item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Meani</hi> of <hi>Perugia</hi> Sargent <hi>Maior.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earle <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> of <hi>Caſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earle <hi>Franceſco</hi> of <hi>Lobi</hi> of <hi>Cremona.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Franceſco Tron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauilla.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Hannibal Adamo</hi> of <hi>Fermo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Scipio</hi> of the Citie of <hi>Caſtello.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Charles Ragonaſco</hi> of <hi>Cremona.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Franceſco Siraco.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Roberto Maluezzo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Ceſar</hi> of <hi>Aduerſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Cap. <hi>Bernardin</hi> of <hi>Agubio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Franceſco Bugon</hi> of <hi>Verona.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Fabiano.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Sebastian del Sole</hi> of <hi>Florence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Hector</hi> of <hi>Breſcia,</hi> the ſucceſſour to the Captaine <hi>Ceſar</hi> of <hi>Aduerſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Flaminio</hi> of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> ſucceſſour vnto <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian del Sole.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Fermo,</hi> ſucceſſour to the Captaine of <hi>Cernole.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Bartholmewe</hi> of <hi>Cernole.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Iohn Battista</hi> of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarole.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Iohn Franceſco</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The names of Chriſtians made Slaues.</head>
               <item>THe Earle <hi>Hercoles Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nengo,</hi> with <hi>Iulius Ceſar Ghelfo</hi> a ſoldier of <hi>Breſſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earle <hi>Nestor Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nengo,</hi> which fled.</item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Marco Criuellatore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12662:25"/>The Lord <hi>Hercoles Malatesta.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Peter Conte</hi> of <hi>Montalberto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Horatio</hi> of <hi>Veletri.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Aluigi Pezano.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Conte <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Corbara.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Iſtria.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Soldatelli</hi> of <hi>Agubio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Aſcoli.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Antony</hi> of the ſame towne.</item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Sebastian</hi> of the ſame towne.</item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Salgano</hi> of the Citie of <hi>Caſtello.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Marcheſe</hi> of <hi>Fermo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Iohn Antonio</hi> of <hi>Pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenza.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Carletto Naldo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Lorenzo Fornaretti.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Barnardo</hi> of <hi>Breſcia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Barnardino Coco.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Simon Bagneſe,</hi> ſucceſſour to the Captaine <hi>Dauid Noce.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Tiberio Ceruto,</hi> ſucceſſour vnto Conte <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Lanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ano,</hi> ſucceſſour vnto Captain <hi>Franceſco Troncauilla.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Morgante,</hi> ſucceſſour to Captaine <hi>Hannibal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lieftenant, ſucceſſour vnto the Captaine <hi>Scipio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Standerdbearer, ſucceſſour to Captaine <hi>Roberto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Ottauio</hi> of <hi>Rimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> ſucceſſour to the Captaine <hi>Franceſco Bugon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Mario da Fabiano,</hi> ſucceſſour to Cap. <hi>Iacomo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Franceſco</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> ſucceſſour vnto Captain <hi>Antonio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Capt. <hi>Matteo</hi> of <hi>Capua.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Iohn Maria</hi> of <hi>Verona.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Captaine <hi>Mancino.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶The Fortifiers.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Marmori.</hi> dead.</item>
               <item>The Knight <hi>Maggio.</hi> ſlaue.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:26"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Turkiſhe Captaines in Famagoſta.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>MVſtafà</hi> Generall.</item>
               <item>The Baſſà of Aleppo.</item>
               <item>The Baſſà of Natolia. <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſafer</hi> Baſſà of Nicoſia.</item>
               <item>The Baſſà of Caramania.</item>
               <item>The Agà of the Giannizers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Giambelat Bey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Sanganccho of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis. <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Begliarbei of Grece.</item>
               <item>The Baſſà of Sciuaſſi &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſco.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ferca Framburaro.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Sangaccho of Antipo. <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Soliman Bey. ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three Sangacchos of Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia. <hi>One ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſtafà Bey,</hi> Generall of the Venturers. <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fergat</hi> Ruler of Malathia. <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Framburaro of Diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:12662:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
